As I get older, I think the rule number
one is don't get injured because they
accumulate. And then number two,
something's better than nothing. So if
for whatever reason, life got in the
way, you were defeated, and you're not
going to be able to make it to the gym
for an hour, it's like, look,
do 10 laps in the pool, do 20 push-ups,
do something. There's no excuse that you
can give that would take those types of
options away. So rather than pushing it
and pushing it and pushing it to another
day, just scaling down to something
minimal. And I think if you do that
consistently, it's pretty hard to lose.
I am going to just hop into it. Take
advantage of everybody being here.
Thanks for joining. There were a lot of
questions submitted, hundreds upon
hundreds. Narrowed that down to a few
dozen and I will answer a handful and
then we'll hop to the live feed and
answer questions there. So the first
question is from Christine and here it
is. Over the years we've watched you
going through quite a transformation
from a driven hyperoptimized logical
business investor to a grounded
relationship focused man talking openly
about trauma, mental health struggles
and meditation. What are your comments
on the transformation? And for someone
who is still stuck in the driven
hyperoptimized logical phase and sees
that they need to change something, what
advice would you give? So the first
observation
or perhaps question I would pose in
response to that is are you stuck? Maybe
you're not stuck. And I say that because
my shift certainly eventually, and it
took me decades to get there, focusing
on
addressing childhood sexual abuse and so
on, which I've written about
extensively, so I won't belabor it here
and drag people into that, was because I
recognized
over time that the 17 separate problems
I thought were separate were in fact all
stemming from this unressed elephant in
the
that required
some
I don't want to say handling maybe it's
metabolizing maybe it's revisiting maybe
it's recontextualizing as an adult so
that was a necessary step for me I
couldn't proceed past go without
addressing that I don't think everyone
requires that and
there are tools I think that almost
anyone can benefit from that may steer
you towards introspection or more
internal validation versus external
validation. Like some of you will
recognize this. The book Awareness by
Anthony Dlo. I still read it at least
once a year. There are frameworks that I
think nearly anyone can benefit from
like IFS internal family systems and I
did a live session on this podcast with
the founder of IFS Richard Schwarz. I
would caution though that just as you
frame the question as being stuck in a
driven hyper optimized phase, it is just
as easy, if not easier, to get stuck in
doing the quote unquote work. And you
only have to visit Austin to see what
I'm talking about. There are lots of
people who can't seem to get past a
hyper reflective
neverending cycle of polishing the self.
And I think that
any obsession with the self, whether
that is validated by others through your
bank account or achievements or getting
pats on the back for doing the quote
unquote work, is poisonous and excess,
right? The dose makes the poison. And I
think it applies here. So I would say
maybe you're not stuck. Number one, that
deserves from some examination. That
deserves some examination.
But I do think awareness, IFS, there are
a handful of things that anyone that I
know certainly has benefited from or can
benefit from. So I would start there.
So I'll leave it there for now.
The next question is from Mike R. Much
of your work focuses on reversible
experiments, but the stakes of
reinvention rise in your late 40s when
career, family, health, plus financial
responsibilities make big moves harder
to test. How would you distinguish a
genuine next chapter from an impulse to
escape your current life? Would you use
a 30-day experiment, or is there a
better framework for evaluating a major
career/life pivot? So, I'm going to try
to keep this short, but I would say read
a blog post by Derek Civers that is
titled There are always more than two
options. And you can find that very
easily, but it is civersopson.
So that's siv.rsoptions.
And let's see if I can pull this up for
a second. And in effect, he says when
people say they only have two options,
it means they got stuck. Once people get
two options, they start comparing pros
and cons of those two and forget to
think of more. As an example, a friend
was trying to decide whether to stick
with his frustrating job or quit and
start his own company. I suggested some
other options. This is all reading from
his blog post. Bullet number one, build
your new company outside of work hours.
Do this until the income from the new
company is 50% of your salary, then
quit. Bullet two, show up to your job
but secretly just work for your own
company all day. Do this until you get
fired. Bullet three, bring your new
company idea to your boss and propose it
as a division of their company so you
can stay on salary. Last bullet, do
neither and move to New Zealand to be a
tour guide. After exploring more
options, my friend realized that he
didn't actually want to start a new
business. He was just avoiding fixing
his current situation. All right. I'm
not saying that's the case for you,
Mike, but I would say that you probably
have a lot of options you could list out
if you took the time. And we all fall
prey to the A versus B trap, but there's
almost you can always come up with C, D,
E, F, and G. So that would be step
number one for me. And then
beyond that, I would say
write down all the things that you find
might lead you to want to escape your
current life, right? What are those? And
I think a lot about something that Chris
Bosch shared in a conversation with me
on this podcast. He's an 11time NBA
All-Star and he talked about in the
context of gratitude metaphorically if
you were to sit around a table and he
might have been crediting someone else
but if you had five people and they all
put all their problems on the table you
would pick your problems right back up.
So sometimes your problems seem really
bad because you are most intimate with
what you experience. But if you were to
take all of the insecurities and
friction and challenges and relationship
wos of your five best friends, put
everything on a table, you might rush to
pick up your own problems again. So I I
would say that
as a thought exercise, that is that is
also valuable.
30-day experiments, I'm always a fan of
two to four week experiments, but you
don't have to make it binary, right? You
could do it after hours, you could do it
on the weekends. This is something that
I've recommended in the 4-hour work week
with respect to developing your own
businesses or lifestyle muses and I
still think it applies to many many many
different things. And coming back to
dose, there may be something that you
really enjoy in small doses. And this
also hearkens back to a story in the
4-hour work week which dives into let's
just say surfing. If you love surfing
maybe on the weekends because it is an
alternative a contrast to what you do
throughout the week that does not mean
that you would enjoy surfing as your job
if you had it as an obligation from
Monday to Friday. Right? So you want to
expand the volume of something like that
to test the hypothesis before you jump
from A to B. So, I'm not sure if that
answers your question super directly,
but that's how I might try to think
through it. All right, next question is
from Nathan B and he talks about, you
know, his father watched electricity
reach his community and these various
technological changes over time and then
I'll hop to the I think the crux of the
question. So
in effect AI feels different and I would
agree with that not merely another tool
but dot dot dot dot dot five-year
predictions now seem almost unserious.
So here's my question. If you were a
capable but nonf famous intellectually
curious person responsible for
protecting and providing for a family
determined to remain useful, healthy,
financially resilient, and morally
grounded. What concrete practices,
skills, relationships, and experiments
would you prioritize during the next 12
months to prepare for the coming decade?
So, that is a tall order. It's a very
good question. I don't know if I can and
I don't think it would be helpful
actually maximally for me to try to
parse that into each bullet point. But I
can tell you how I've been thinking
about this with respect to teaching
children or upskilling yourself or maybe
creating a flack jacket of sorts. And I
have approached this from dozens of
different angles and I keep coming back
to
learning,
asking questions, written and verbal
communications and negotiating. Those
are a handful of skills that I think
will remain constant. And I could defend
each of those, but I will say that with
AI and certainly with so many people
having their massive bank accounts and
net worths tied into this, there is a
lot of selling of all of the change that
is coming. And there is a lot of change
that is already here and it's going to
accelerate. But
the more things change, the more certain
things I think remain constant, right?
The necessity of in real life close
human relationships is not going away as
a prerequisite for mental and spiritual
health, right? That social component, we
could just call it social health, which
includes all of that. But I would focus
on learning. And this is going to sound
like I'm shilling my own bags here, but
the metalarning section of the 4-hour
chef, I think the 4-hour chef is a book,
tried to do too much, but the very first
section, which is something like 80
pages on metalarning, I do think is
worth a revisit if you haven't in a
while. And learning once you try to
break it down into its constituent
building blocks
really comes down in many cases to
asking questions. And the asking of
questions is important not just for
interviewing other people or asking
questions of other people to try to
separate fact from fiction. It's equally
important for asking yourself questions.
And this is where all things are
interrelated and awareness by Anthony
Dlo and so on will tie into this 8020
analysis. It's really a collection of
questions for examining your assumptions
and separating signal from noise. Uh so
we come down to asking questions and
then we have written communications and
verbal communication. And I think in
many cases and Kevin Kelly for instance
the founding editor of Wired magazine
would say that he doesn't write what he
knows. He writes in order to better
understand what he thinks to figure out
what he thinks. And I don't think these
are going away. Uh, sure you could try
to just walk and talk into an LLM, and I
do that as well, but there's a lot of
bias built into that, not just by the
people who design the systems, but by
the force of memory function across
different chats and threads, you're
going to get a lot of self-reinforcing
feedback. So, I do think getting offline
like I did today, I spent 90% of my day
today with pen and paper. And maybe that
just dates me as a boomer, but I don't
think so. It removes distraction and I'm
able to be much more nonlinear off of a
keyboard where I have to hit return to
go down, right? I really like to use
arrows and so on. So, anything that will
improve written comms, there are many
books on this certainly on writing well
by Zincer. Verbal comms you can, it's
going to sound so antiquated, but like
join a local toast masters or something
like that. get used to standing up and
talking and that would be on the group
side and then separately negotiating
that's not going anywhere. So learning
how to propose and craft deal structure
for in most cases ideally win-win
outcomes but that's not reality 100% of
the time but negotiating whether that's
and these are some older callbacks for
me but the secrets of power negotiating
by Dawson I remember had a huge impact
on me getting past no had a large impact
on me there are other books that provide
frameworks and I've interviewed a lot of
these people so you can also
look at the archive of the podcast for
people involved with the Harvard
negotiating project and I actually
interviewed one of the co-authors of
getting to yes it's William Yuri and
those are all worth jumping into but
learning asking questions written comms
verbal comms and negotiating is really
where I would focus. I think that those
are
meta skills that can be applied across
disciplines to almost every everything
and anything. So that's probably where I
would focus in terms of morally
grounded. I mean, man, read philosophy.
Philosophy is not for people in academic
ivory towers. In my opinion, if you look
back, it's learning how to live. And I
think that you can establish consistent
moral codes. Religion would be another
option. Certainly not averse to that.
There are many different paths to the
same goal, which is having rules that
you follow consistently that allow you
to view yourself as a morally grounded
person. All right. Next is [snorts]
from Mason H. when you returned from
your sbatical in 2024. So FYI, on the
10th anniversary of the podcast, some of
you might remember I took a four-month
hiatus where we republished episodes. I
didn't record or publish any new
episodes. And part of this was to
experiment with Killing the Golden
Goose. Does the world end? When I bench
the goose for a short period of time and
I had a lot of fear around that. Turns
out, as with most fears, it was
ungrounded
and it was fine. But here's the
question. When you returned from your
sobatical in 2024, you set a new set of
rules for the kind of podcast you were
going to do moving forward. Which of
those rules have made it in the last two
years and which did you discard?
Any generalizable insights for those of
us trying to stay in blue oceans in our
own endeavors? All right. So, the last
part about generalizing, I would say if
you haven't read it, read the blue ocean
strategy. It is going to be increasingly
critical and important and certainly for
a lot of businesses existential
in the coming years. This is going to
become more and more valuable real
estate to figure out how to navigate.
All right, so the blue ocean strategy.
The other generalizable insight would be
fear setting. Use that exercise. You can
find it for free online. I did a TED
talk about it. You don't have to buy
anything. Use that to stress test your
fears related to any action. What is
holding you back? Right? What are the
costs of inaction? It's all laid out
very clearly. So look at that. But to
answer your question, I thought why rely
on my recollection? Because sometimes
our own assessments and recollection,
memory is an act of creating or
recreating might be self- serving,
right? I I might hallucinate to look at
things more favorably. So I asked one of
my key employees what his answer would
be and the rules that stuck which ended
up being very gratifying. Number one, no
book launching episodes, right? So
changing the rules around book launches.
That was probably the biggest change.
Just did not want to be in the podcast
aosphere rotation of the same guests
being on 20 podcasts at a time. Number
two, living legends.
wanted to interview people who are older
who perhaps had either not been on
podcasts or might not be on many
podcasts before they could no longer do
that and operate at a high level for a
few hours. So we had Andrew Won 84,
Richard Baylor 80, Tish Robbie 74, Wayde
Davis 72, David White, Frank Miller,
Danny Hillis, right? There are many
examples and whether or not these
episodes had maximum downloads, I would
not expect them to because a lot of
these names are relatively unknown
compared to celebrities certainly and
everything is being pushed to short
clips with name recognition or
sensational stuff and I try to avoid
both of those. I really enjoyed doing
this and the only way I'm gonna have any
endurance
in playing any game I choose to play,
which includes podcasting, is if I enjoy
doing it. Because if I enjoy doing it, I
have this prerequisite foundational
layer of energy which allows me in turn
to have attention which allows me to
take advantage of time and outlast
trends. Okay? So, and that could still
be a fatality, right? If everything gets
pushed to LLMs or whatever, but you get
the idea. Number three, experiments. So,
co-hosting episodes with like Nick
Kakonis, Kevin Kelly, I should do more
of that. So, it was nice to do this
review. Thank you for the question.
guided meditations with Henry Shookman,
the meditation Mondays. If you haven't
had a chance to check those out, go
check them out. You will feel better if
you incorporate them. Tim's Foundry
Kitchen, haven't given up on that one.
I'm going to do more of that. That
actually had a lot of impact behind the
scenes, but again, wasn't one of the
most downloaded episodes of the last
year. But in terms of impact in a few
very important ways that we were
tracking that are not reflected on
Spotify or Apple podcasts very
successful and then the simplify your
life episodes which I really really
really enjoyed doing those compilations
then we had a couple of household names
right we had a handful of household
names Tim Mcgra and so on which were fun
so that 9010 split meaning I'm going to
interview people in a barbell strategy
who are either relatively unknown like
Tish Robbie who's the air parent of Dr.
Seuss. Amazing story. You should check
it out. Last name is spelled R A B or
Tim McGirl, right? Almost everybody,
let's just say within certain
demographics knows who that is. A lot of
fun. And people who also who have just
not been on podcasts like Steve Young.
All right, so that is the answer to that
question. All right, the next one is
from Alec B.
And my answer will be pretty short to
this. I'm a therapist, so building
emotional closeness is literally my job,
and it's always come easy with women.
But I've never cracked male friendship.
If you were a 30-some with zero old
friend groups to lean on, what's the
actual first move? And how do you get
past how weird it feels to initiate with
another guy? All right, let me tell a
story first. So, I was in the mountains
of Montana with a small group of guys.
This has shown up in some of my writing
a couple months ago. and we're sitting
around this fire chatting and we're
having these really deep conversations
after a full day of activities together.
All right, so while we're doing the
activities, we're hiking, we're carrying
weight, we're tending llamas, long
story, we're fishing, we're like
climbing over rocks and doing stuff that
is somewhat dangerous. All of that is
activities together. And then late at
night, I think me there was some tea.
There might have been some whiskey. Who
knows? And later on, we were going to
grab some really magnified binoculars
and look at the full moon standing up on
a rock, which ended up being incredible,
by the way, if you have something with a
stabilizer. But while we were around the
fire, we were having this very deep
conversation. And one of the guys there
said, "You know why this works so well?"
And he said, "You know why also perhaps
men in particular, and not saying this
is limited to men, but love fires so
much, is no eye contact. You're staring
at the fire. It's not some weird sitdown
session where two guys are staring at
each other, which I think activates some
type of
millions of year old machinery that
reads as threat. We're just sitting
around a fire. No one's making eye
contact. It's kind of dark and we're
talking about all of this deep stuff,
right? But it was a relatively small
percentage of the total day. And this is
a long way of saying that I think men
and women are pretty different and women
are much more adept at the face-to-faced
verbal social element for lots of
fantastic evolutionary reasons. And uh I
think men just require and I'm talking
about like I guess like uh
heteronormative whatever whatever but
maybe not. That's my reference point of
course is shared activities. Men just
bond in different ways and I've tried
both. I've tried everything in between.
I've tried the extremes, right? And I
would just find activities. There was
another question from someone else about
moving to a new city. How would you
build relationships?
My answer would be to
really have all of it revolve around
shared activities. So, take your pick,
right? Is it morning swims? I like to do
something active. Is it rock climbing?
Is it fill in the blank? Something
inherently social where you have a
partner or people you're working with?
Maybe it's a run, right?
That is followed by some beers on fill
in the blank place, right? There's a lot
of this stuff out there. But those are
some of my thoughts. May not be the most
research supported, but I think it's
evolutionarily supported. And certainly
when I look at all of my male friends
who have the closest male friendships,
whether they are from 20 years ago or
from a year or two ago, shared projects
or shared activities is the answer. And
I have some relatively new male
friendships, say with Alan Lee. Have we
had a lot of deep conversations? Yeah.
But did we spend a year like building a
card game together? Yes. You get to see
kind of through the cracks
and indirectly talk about a lot of deep
stuff without actually
opening the kimono and talking about it
head-on, right? And I think that's one
example that comes to mind. All right,
long answer, but let's hop into the live
questions. I'm going to see what we have
here. Thank you, Hannah. Love your
episodes with women authors like Annne
Lamont, Liz Gilbert, Margaret Atwood,
and Cheryl Strade. Yeah, for sure. Mary
car is also just phenomenal. If you
haven't heard that one, check that one
out, please. All right, question about
the Saint protocol. This is a TMS
protocol that I've used for generalized
anxiety disorder and OCD. I have
actually tested a number of things since
can be incredibly effective getting in
some people 70 to or I should say some
groups of people 70 to 80% remission in
treatment resistant depression, things
like that. So, it's accelerated TMS.
You're applying basically a paddle or a
helmet to your head to affect different
brain regions. And sometimes it's not so
much a chemical issue. You just have
anatomical structures that are kind of
firing in the wrong order, right? It's
as if you were trying to say drive a
manual car, but you were using the
clutch and shifting the gears and so on
out of order. You kind of have to get
those in the right sequence. And I'm
simplifying, but this is one way to look
at it.
There is a company that I recently got
involved with maybe six to 12 months ago
called Ampa Health AMA and Jonathan
Downer, Dr. Jonathan Downer is involved
with this company and they have
developed a one-day protocol. So instead
of 5 days, which is sane, you're getting
10 stimulations a day. It's pretty much
all you're doing for a week. What
they've done is compress that into a
single day and they with what they call
the 1D protocol they pre-administer a
drug called descloerene which is
actually an antibiotic. They just give
you a small amount that induces helps
induce plasticity.
So I was able to get 3 to four months of
complete relief after one day which is
bananas. I mean it still blows my mind.
And I'm focused at this point more on
these ultra condensed, possibly
pharmacologically enhanced options
because most people can't take 5 days
off of work. Most people can't afford
what is involved in traveling to 5 days
of treatment, but a single day suddenly
really opens up the aperture of who this
could help. So I am paying a lot of
attention to that area and might have
more on that soon. question from Craig.
I'm gonna keep trying to answer these.
There's a lot of questions coming in, so
it kind of got bumped, but Craig was
asking me keys to building a long-term
dedicated fan base. Honestly, the best
advice I could give, I think, is just
like be try to be your authentically
weird self and follow your own
obsessions. And if something at least in
the non-fiction space, right, if you are
contending with a problem,
a challenge, a dream, and you're trying
to figure out how to get to that, I
think the personal is the most
universal. So don't try to read the tea
leaves to guess what your audience
wants. Just do what is interesting to
you, right? Don't be ashamed of your
obsessions. And that's going to come up
in some later answers as well.
And if you do that, you know, at least
you're taking care of yourself along the
way. You know, there's a lot more to it,
but the tools, the platforms, the
formats, all of that changes over time,
but this is how I think about it. And
also, I'm not aiming to impact a 100
million people, right? I'm like, well,
this helped me. Maybe it'll help
somebody else. Let me take good notes.
I'll share it. And if it really helps
five people, I will consider that very,
very well worth the time.
All right, moving down. Sebio, still
using kettle bells in your training.
What's an average week of training look
like for me recently? I do still use
kettle bells, especially for overhead
pressing. I don't do as much swinging as
I used to simply because of some lower
spinal issues. But I will do cleans and
then from cleans into shoulder pressing.
My workout routine right now is pretty
simple. The backbone, pun intended, of
that is lifting two to three times a
week. That really is the crux of it. I
just think for longevity,
weight training, if I had to choose one
modality, would be the pick. So, I'm
roughly breaking that into pushing
exercises, pulling exercises, and legs.
And those are my three weight training
workouts per week. Each one's about an
hour. Then yoga, one to two times a
week. I really like a yangar yoga
specifically for alignment and use of
props and so on. It's very adaptable in
that way. And then some form of movement
daily. Biking, swimming, walking. And as
I get older, I think the rule number one
is don't get injured because they
accumulate. And then number two,
something's better than nothing. So, if
for whatever reason, life got in the
way, you were defeated, and you're not
going to be able to make it to the gym
for an hour, it's like, look,
do 10 laps in the pool, do 20 push-ups,
do something. There's no excuse that you
can give that would take those types of
options away. So, rather than pushing it
and pushing it and pushing it to another
day, just scaling down to something
minimal. And I think if you do that
consistently, it's pretty hard to lose
over time. And that was
overlapping a lot with a question from
Barbara C. How are you staying fit these
days physically, mentally, and
soulfully? Mentally and soulfully,
honestly, it's having being very clear
on the one or two things that you are
focused on, say professionally. and then
being very very clear on the one or two
relationships that you are focused on
most. And then booking stuff with your
friend group. And you you can identify
the most quote unquote important friends
for all of those things I just mentioned
by doing a past year review. And people
can look up past year review to see how
I do that. That'll pop right up. All
right. Here's one from Stephen. What
workouts from the 4-hour body are you
still prioritizing in your routines?
There's there's a lot from the 4-hour
body. In the reversing injuries chapter,
you had chop and lift, those types of
exercises where you're basically in a
half kneeling position with a cable
pulley and you're rotating from kind of
like bottom right to top left or say top
right to bottom left or switching to the
other side. I think that kettle bells
still have a place, right? I'm not doing
as many swings, but doing single sided,
you know, one arm presses, for instance,
with kettle bells can, I think, be
incredibly effective for the time
invested. I am certainly using some
variant of AAM's protocol. So, typically
in my weightlifting workouts, I'm going
to be doing very strength focused stuff.
So, it might be kind of greasing the
groove along the lines of Pavle Tatsulin
where I'm doing 10 sets of two pull-ups,
right, with like 30 to 60 seconds in
between, very submaximal, right? And
then at the end of the workout, I'll do
some type of pulling movement with a
5-second up 5-second down cadence to
failure. Right? So, that would be
reminiscent of AAM's protocol. And you
know by and large if you look at my body
I mean it has from a body composition
perspective strength perspective the
spine issues have affected axial loading
top down loading somewhat but you know
I've been able to maintain very very
well between say 30 and almost 50 now.
So if you look at it like what I'm doing
seems to be working. There are always
tweaks to be made, but I think simple
works where complex fails a lot of the
time. All right, this is from Aaron G.
Imagine that your next podcast guest is
a high school senior who will become one
of the most successful people of their
generation, but today they look
completely average. What skills,
abilities, qualities would you be
listening for that teachers or schools
often overlook? This is pretty simple
and this is also how I find a lot of
interesting technologies, stuff on the
cutting edge
before it makes it to the mainstream.
And that can inform how you invest. That
can inform how you think about life.
It's just a fun way to explore
this thing called being human. I would
look at what they're doing on the
weekends and evenings. Probably I would
look at what these kids are doing
related to their obsessions. What are
their obsessions? Are they doing any
projects? Are they using initiative to
create things?
Are those approaches unorthodox? Are
they self-eing? If they're teaching
themselves something, what are they
teaching themselves? Right? And what are
the lessons beneath that? Because you
might be tempted to dismiss something
quickly. If it's like, ah, okay, it's
Minecraft. Who cares? It's like, well,
hold on a second. You know, what is that
actually teaching? All right, which
elements of that are they best at? All
right, which elements are they most
interested in? All right,
those are the types of things that I
would be looking for. All right, next
one is Niha G. How do you distinguish
between needing a vacation, being burned
out, and simply having outgrown the life
you've built? And once you realize
you've outgrown it, what would you do to
hone in on what needs to change? I'm
only going to address the first part of
that. So, how do you distinguish between
needing a vacation, being burned out,
and simply having outgrown the life
you've built? So, step number one would
be take a vacation. since that is a
temporary intervention and if that fixes
the problem then you know that perhaps
was the answer right so if you're asking
yourself a question is it abcd or should
I do abcd if there's one that is of
short duration try it cross it off the
list right that would be the first thing
and then you know being burned out might
be related to needing a vacation and
then simply having outgrown the life
you've built I would say take a mini
retirement and
That is another concept from the 4-hour
work week. I still do it once or twice a
year. This is taking
ideally at least three or four weeks
away from your usual routine or
business, right? And I frame it in or
through the lens of business for say
entrepreneurs a lot. This is most
applicable to people who are
self-employed or most easily applied
although literally thousands of people
who have done this who are employed. So
there's flexibility. But the the reason
three or four weeks is important is that
if you take a week off, maybe even two
and you don't change anything before you
leave,
you can try to triage while you're gone.
So you'll be tempted to hop in and put
out small fires before they become big
fires. And when you come back, you can
end up doing two to three weeks of
damage control to reverse all the things
that went wrong. When it's three or four
weeks or 5, 6, 7, 8 weeks, all of a
sudden, before you leave, you have to
take a very hard look at your systems,
your policies, how well you are
eliminating things, automating things.
If you're doing a lot of things that
don't need to be done in the first
place, you might stop those. You might
hit pause on a bunch of things for that
three to four week period and see what
happens. Much like I did with my podcast
soatical, right? And by doing that once
or twice a year, you're effectively
doing a controlled burn, which prevents
much bigger forest fires and it gives
you also perspective much like writing a
book. Right now, I am on a new draft of
a book and I let it sit for a few weeks
because I cannot look at it with fresh
eyes. I'm too close to all the problems
in every edit until I've let it marinate
for a few weeks. So, the benefit of a
mini retirement, and I'm sure people
have written about this online, so you
don't necessarily have to buy the 4-hour
work week, is that you have to set up
systems and policies and improve all of
that before you leave. And by the way,
leave could mean that you're in the same
place, although I do recommend a change
of geography for this.
And then when you come back, you will
also be able to look at things with
fresh eyes and a clearer vision I would
say. Right? So that is probably the
approach that I would take when I am in
doubt
or a lot of different problems are
starting to cohhere together and I'm
having trouble separating them.
In the immediate term, I will start
doing TM meditation again twice a day.
Right? Arnold Schwarzenegger found this.
A lot of problems tend to glom on to one
another and it seems unresolvable.
Meditation twice a day, specifically
twice a day is important. You could also
use, you know, the Way app by Henry
Shooklin or someone else. Twice a day is
important. And I have theories for why
that's the case, but just do that for
like a week or two. And then if there's
still lots of outstanding questions and
it just seems like you're spinning too
many plates, I will try to get a mini
retirement on the calendar. And it
doesn't need to be next week. could be
two months, three months from now, but
get it on the calendar and then defend
it. That is how I approach it. May or
may not apply to your situation.
Hopefully that wasn't boring as
Next question is,
I'm not sure if this is going to be
helpful, but I'll just throw it out
there because it's a simple response. Is
McKinley W. And I apologize if this is a
dissatisfying answer on my part, but I
work in public education. and have spent
years in child and teen mental health
and suicide prevention. Thank you for
that first and foremost. It's super
important work. What advice would you
give to practitioners and educators who
are caring for our youth through
unprecedented times? I'm going to just
hop in for a second. I would look very
very closely at Jonathan Height Hi Dt
not only his books but also what he's
doing with his small group of
researchers. They've actually changed
certain legislation on a state-by-state
basis for restricting phone use in
schools and I think it's very very
interesting. So take a look at that.
Getting back to the question, you've had
many great guests who have touched on
this and you've shared boldly about your
own experience. What would you say to a
16-year-old in 2026?
I would say that,
you know, this
everything on this Black Mirror is
designed to hijack your free will and to
turn you into a puppet of the machine of
some type, one machine or another,
whether that's meta or fill in the
blank, right? And
that
this could be a digital mini retirement.
I would try to get them off of social
media for a period of time and then talk
to them. Be like, "Hey, this is going to
be an experiment. You can get back on it
and use it 10 times as much, but I'm
going to challenge you and we're going
to come up with a plan for other things
that you can do. Delete the apps from
your phone for 3 to four weeks. We're
going to do an assessment beforehand to
look at how you feel, your anxiety
levels, maybe depressive symptoms, how
much you're getting done, what you say
you want to do versus how you're
spending time. And then we're going to
look at it afterwards. And no
expectations, no pressure on what you do
with those results. But let's start
there. And you know, if you want to have
a beautiful life that has some element
of peace of mind and healthy
relationships, I think it'll benefit
you. If you want to be a world beater
and you want to build anything or
operate at the highest levels in any
way, also this will help you. So, I
would probably pitch it that way. That's
what I would do. All right.
Next one is going to be a little inside
baseball, but I'm going to jump into it
because it's a topic that I love. This
is from Sebastian, and I'm going to
abbreviate this a little bit. All right,
so I've talked a lot about language
learning in the past, and I've had blog
posts and resources from people like
Benny Lewis, the Irish Polyglot. And
Seb's question or Seby's question is,
has any of this thinking changed with
advancements in AI?
And here are some questions. What's the
purpose of language learning? If in the
end we're all plugged in with a chip and
blah blah blah, what does language
learning provide for the human
experience? So for me, number one,
actually population level, zoom out.
There seem to be some crazy longevity
and cognitive benefits to language
learn. This is relatively new. I put it
in the fib Friday newsletter, so I can't
recall it from memory, which is ironic.
I get it. But there seem to be some
really significant benefits to acquiring
multiple languages. Secondly, it doesn't
take that long to get conversationally
functional in a new language. You
probably know this already, but between
8 to 12 weeks, and not to beat a dead
horse, but again, the metalarning
section of the 4-hour chef goes into
this at length. And I've written a lot
on the blog, Tim. I think there's a
section called language learning, but if
you just search language learning,
you'll be able to find a ton of stuff.
So, it's also not as heavy a lift as
people expect, right? To get to a point
where you have a thousand words, you can
go to a country and navigate
80% of your transactional conversations
in a restaurant, at a hotel, whatever,
all in your target language. You could
probably actually do that in about 2
weeks. I know that sounds crazy,
but I believe that is entirely
achievable. And I've taught people to do
that. There are plenty of other people
out there who teach folks. it's very
very achievable right so it seems like
limited downside in terms of time
investment and very high durable upside
but the purpose of language learning for
me also is that you know I agree with
vitkinstein that the limits of our
language are the limits of our world and
there are whether it's through
grammatical structure or vocabulary or
words like you know saaji in Portuguese
which is actually pretty close to like
nutskashi in Japanese or right this term
for dappled light in Japanese
or the phrases like Maywaku in Japanese
which is
people have heard
right
is like pain in the ass. So Maywoko is
like when somebody does you a favor you
don't walk when someone does you like a
favor you don't really want or gives you
a gift you don't want and then you feel
obliged to do stuff for them and it's a
huge pain in the ass. All of that is
compressed into this one expression
which is just beautiful, hilarious, fun.
And we've all heard that, you know, the
Inuit have 30 words for different types
of snow. Hawaiians have many, many, many
different words for various types of
rain. Also, some of them are location
dependent, like rain at a specific
place. All of these concepts broaden
your ability to experience life, right?
In the same way that if you're looking
around here where I'm sitting or you're
driving around and
walking through the woods, let's just
say, and what you see are trees. That's
what you see, trees and plants. But you
don't have any specific knowledge that
allows you to see anything really more
than that. Perhaps somebody could put
two different types of leaves in your
hand. You'd be able to say, "Yes,
they're different." But if you went on a
walk, as I will do with say a botist or
somebody who works at a local
plant shop, doesn't have to cost much
money, be 20 bucks. And they start to
describe to you, for instance, oh,
you're in upstate New York. Here are the
six to eight trees that constitute more
than 90% of all the trees, right? And
here's how you tell them apart. And by
the way, here are the three different
leaf structures that matter. Or with
birds, here's how owl feet are different
from pasarine, which are different from
this. Right? Suddenly, because you have
these labels,
your experience of reality is much
higher resolution. And when it's higher
resolution, when you have also, and
these are not exactly the same thing,
but a better frame rate, I think you
extend your experiential lifespan. All
right? Right. So, if you want to live in
full color HD as opposed to black and
white, and if you want to be able to
watch super slow-mo,
right, to extend your life without
waiting for some magical biological
intervention that all the billionaires
are funding to live forever. Probably
not going to happen anytime soon. You
can do that right now. And one of the
ways that I find helps is by learning
languages. All right, [snorts] that was
a that was a long one. And I didn't even
get to the second part. All right. So,
have I thought about how to
systematically integrate AI into
language learning process.
There are lots of people who have lots
of takes on this. And you know, I was
one of their earliest investors, so I'm
I'm kind of biased here, but I don't
think so. You know, like if anyone's
going to crack AI for language learning,
I do think it's going to be Dolingo.
They're already using it. There may be
some AI native companies that approach
it, but I do think Duolingo is probably
ahead of the game. There are lots of
other options. So for instance, just in
the last few weeks, Instagram
autodubbing has become really good and
my team sent me a clip of me speaking in
Japanese, right? So the random show and
there was a segment and it was my voice.
It sounds like me dubbed into, as far as
I can tell, perfect Japanese, idiomatic
perfect Japanese. And I was like, "Holy
Now, I don't want to spend all day
listening to myself, but because I knew
the content of that conversation,
I was able to improve my my Japanese,
which is already pretty good. It's not
perfect, but it's advanced. I was able
to improve my Japanese in five minutes
of watching something, watching content
I knew in this target language, right?
So, you can use AI. I think one of the
more interesting
uses of AI for language learning for
kids specifically or younger people uh
older people too would be personalizing
the experience based on your interests
based on what you want to learn.
What native content can I aggregate that
will be interesting to you? Right? Like
the Dualingo Spanish podcast was
phenomenal. I don't know what the
equivalent is in Mandarin. I'm trying to
brush up on my Mandarin Chinese right
now. And it's like, well, I would love
to do that. So, I'm going to go to, and
I just did this earlier today, ChatGpt
or Claude, and ask them that question. I
liked the Dualingo Spanish podcast,
which by the way, at one point was like
one of the top 10 podcasts or 20
podcasts in the world. Crazy. And I want
the equivalent for Mandarin. What might
that look like? Now, if it doesn't
exist, I would imagine that within a
year, AI will be able to create that for
me. And that would be a great use case
for me for AI enhancing language
learning. But frankly, old and boring
and analog I think works fantastic
because as soon as you are learning a
language on this, you are competing,
your attention is competing with a
thousand other distractions that are
more tantalizing than using spaced
repetition or super memo or something
like that. Ani to acquire vocabulary,
right? So,
I like printed out flashcards. I like
watching, for instance, anytime you're
watching Netflix or whatever, Amazon
Prime. Okay, here's the thing. I don't
actually believe you learn a target
language. Let's say Italian. I've been
watching some Italian movies recently. I
love Italian as a language.
I can watch, say, Roberto Benini.
Incredible, right? Life is beautiful.
But if I miss something and I'm watching
English subtitles, if I miss it, I miss
it. I don't get it. However, if I have
spent, let's just say 72 hours getting
using a
Lonely Planet phrase book intended for
travelers about Italian. They give you
like a 10-page grammar overview. If I
have a basic understanding, then I can
watch a movie I know in and out, right?
Die Hard Babe is one of my favorites.
the born identity, whatever, where you
know the dialogue,
snatch, whatever it might be, and then
just turn on the subtitles in your
target language. So now I'm watching,
like right now I'm watching Parks and
Wreck, and we're going to come back to
Parks and Wreck, but I'm watching from
season 1, episode 1 through Parks and
Wreck. It's highly conversational, lots
of different characters, and you can
watch it as you would normally watch it,
or you can just turn on some subtitles
in whatever your target language is, and
you will acquire a lot of language, a
lot of vocab. All right, so not sure
that is helpful, but that's how I'm
thinking about it. And I'm definitely
going to be learning more languages, so
I do think about this. All right, let's
hop into.
And my laptop battery is doing so well.
I can't believe I've ever recorded
podcasts indoors. Ludicrous. Should
always do it outside with nice weather
like this. All right, I'm going to hop
back into the live chat and see if we
got anything I can hop into. Also, some
of you have heard me talk about this.
Michelle Thomas. M I C H E L T H O M A
S. Michelle Thomas method. If you want
something you can listen to and really
acquire the fundamentals of a language
in a week or two, the Michelle Thomas
method is outstanding. The languages he
recorded himself, which I think are
French, Spanish, Italian, maybe
certainly German are world class. The
Korean that I went through, I was very
skeptical that anyone other than
Michelle would be able to use his method
to teach well, and it was awesome.
So, I would I would take a very close
look at Michelle Thomas. His background
is nuts. Okay.
Michael R. What's one of your recent
favorite TV shows or movies? All-time
favorite TV shows or movies? Well, I've
I just mentioned some of my favorite
movies. And when I'm writing a new book,
very often I'll write late at night and
I will take one of my favorite movies
and I'll play it on the TV or on a
projector and mute it and then I'll just
listen to music. But I like having the
company late at night so it doesn't feel
too isolating. And it's been different
movies for different books. But I mean
I've seen Babe like a thousand times.
I've seen Born Identity like a thousand
times. Spirited Away I've probably seen
a few hundred times cuz I'm playing them
every night, right? And there are many
others right now. And this comes to a
question someone else asked. Len a I've
always enjoyed your what purchase under
$100 has made a big impact question. Why
have you stopped asking that? I don't
have a great answer to that. And do you
have any new purchases that would make
such a list? And this ties into favorite
TV shows. All right. So, I had like
millions of people, I had seen many
short clips on social of parks and
wreck, parks and recreation. I'd even
seen one or two episodes, but I had
never watched it as the good Lord
intended, which is from season 1,
episode one all the way through. And
there are 120 plus episodes and goodness
gracious is that a fantastic show. It is
just wholesome goodness, you know, 90%
of the time. I think familyfriendly 99%
of the time. Not that I care about that
right now, but it's so positive and such
a feelgood pallet cleanser given the
insanity that we get waterboarded with
all day through doom scrolling. And even
if you don't want to be subjected to it,
it's just everywhere. It really has
turned into this nightly ritual with my
lady and we just watch one episode every
night, one or two. So good. And that's
literally months and months of payoff
because they have seven seasons. So
buying the full seven seasons is my best
purchase of under $100. This is from
Timothy K. You've said walking is my
number one daily hack. I'm just
revisiting the memory banks to try to
confirm that I've said that, but doesn't
really matter what actually happens in
my mind on those walks. that doesn't
happen at a desk intentional or does it
just unfold?
I will say that it's it's not always
about what happens in the mind. I just
pay even though I might be known in some
circles as a early stage tech investor
and blah blah blah blah blah. So, I'm
looking at the new new new new new new
thing. I pay more attention to the old
old old thing and evolutionary drives
that have withtood millennia and
millions of years
to prove durable. And we're designed to
move. We're designed to walk a lot,
right? And most of us don't do as much
of that as we have evolved to be capable
of. So, I just find the health benefits,
the mood elevation.
It is across the board beneficial to me.
If I'm walking, sometimes it's going to
be just letting my mind wander, trying
to let ideas percolate from wherever the
muse might yank them if I'm working on a
book, might be listening to an audio
book, might be doing phone calls. But
walking, walking, walking. I mean,
there's you can fix a lot of problems by
walking. And when I say walking, I mean
walking like two hours plus a day is a
lot of walking. But for me, like any
amount of walking helps, but just like
meditating twice a day is fundamentally
different for me. Like if you can
meditate,
for instance, like if you could choose
15 minutes twice a day or 30 minutes
once a day, I do 15 minutes twice a day.
And similarly with the walking, any
amount helps, but
there seems to be something kind of
magical that happens after at least an
hour, right? Preferably two. So that's
that's where I'll leave that. My top tip
for more restful sleep at the moment
when falling asleep is fine, but hitting
a full night's rest is challenging.
I think that's a question.
I mean, number one, look, if you're
waking up to pee a lot, stop drinking
water an hour or two before you go to
bed, two hours, right? Just like stop
drinking so much water. I drink water
compulsively, right? So, that is
something that I have to tell myself.
And putting aside drugs and all that
kind of stuff cuz I don't think we want
to get into that rabbit hole right now.
you know, falling asleep for me. So,
cutting down on primary insomnia or
onset insomnia.
The TMS, the one day TMS has just been
remarkable for that.
So, people can look up Ampa Health if
they want to try to find a place that
might offer a one day. It's called the
1D protocol. You can also look up
literature on that. But otherwise, sun
lots of exercise. So boring. Isn't that
boring? But if I get plenty of sun
exposure,
if I'm seeing lots of natural light,
especially when the sun is going down,
like right now, I mean, in the morning,
yes, to wake up, but also plenty of
light exposure
and I am exercising so that I feel
tired. It sounds so ridiculous for me to
seg, but it bears repeating because it I
think in modern environments, and modern
life, it's very easy to do what? to
suffer from a deficiency of sunlight,
get very little sunlight exposure, and
to not be tired because you're sitting
in front of one of these screens at 18
in for the majority of the day. So,
those would be a few. It's another
reason why I like to walk because I can
get a lot done if I push this horrible
thing called the inbox to phone calls
and then just do a few hours of calls,
which I do almost every Tuesday when I'm
having one-on-one calls with my direct
reports as an example.
Let me know if you have follow-ups on
that, but that's what comes to mind.
This is a question uh let's see if I can
answer this. I didn't have immediate
thoughts. This is a question from
Oxanna. As someone who naturally values
privacy, how did you reconcile that with
choosing such a public career and has
that changed over time? Well, the first
thing I would say is that I didn't
really
think through choosing a public career
because the first book was turned down
by 25 plus publishers and then bought
for nothing. And my expectation was that
it wasn't going to do very much. And
even though I stacked the deck so that
it would have a snowballs chance in
hell, I did not expect it to blow up.
And by the time it did blow up and then
I was saying yes to things and became
publicly exposed, the genie was out of
the bottle, toothpaste was out of the
out of the toothpaste tube, however you
want to think about it.
But if I could hit, you know, control Z,
there are times when I would be tempted
to say yes, I would take that. And I
think the silver lining on it is that
the half-life of fame is just getting
shorter and shorter and shorter. Some of
you might remember, let's just call it
10 years ago, you would get a hilarious
meme video and that video would make the
rounds for like a week. How long do the
videos make the rounds now? 60 seconds,
3 hours, one day.
It's everything is becoming more
ephemeral in the world of sort of
digital visibility and over time like I
might you know shut of the podcast or
stop doing video
because I have no no desire for more
facial recognition.
But I think depending on what you're
trying to do, for better and for worse,
if you're maybe in growth mode, it's
going to get harder and harder to have
any kind of
durable public profile. Now, on the flip
side, it's going to get easier and
easier for everyone to find you. So, I
do think it's important to think about
digital protections, privacy
protections, and so on. But that's a
much longer conversation for another
time. But yes, I am paranoid and
incredibly
focused on privacy. I think that privacy
in some ways, even though it was a let's
call it a god-given right for millennia
upon millennia,
it is now a luxury of sorts, right? If
you do not take proactive action, if you
do not have defenses put up, like your
whole life is on display or available
for the right for the right technical
person who can do a deep dive or for the
right price, right? So, you really and
there are tools you can use like incogns
for scraping stuff off the web. I think
that's just going to become a privacy
survival imperative if you want it. Then
there's other stuff that's interesting.
You know, if you want like private
money, right, which by the way, like for
a long time, cash was that. Now it's
like go to your bank and try to take out
$9,000. You're going to get
cross-examined. Government doesn't like
private money, even though the default
was kind of fiat currency for a long
time, which allowed you to kind of live
your life and do your thing without
having big brother breathing on your
face at every second. So, you know,
stuff like Zcash is kind of interesting.
Obviously, crypto can lead you into
dangerous waters and you can lose
everything very quickly. But I do find
some of the privacy coins and stuff
interesting. So, we'll see where all
that goes. That does not mean invest, by
the way. It is very, very easy to lose
all your money in that stuff. All right.
This one is from Josh. Tim, what are
three to five things in your life now
that you happily pay top dollar for? In
other words, what luxuries do you think
are absolutely worth upgrading for?
I'm going to mention a few. The first is
massage and manual therapy. And I wanted
to mention this first because even when
I was very poor right out of school and
driving around in a used handme-down
minivan that the the rear seats have
been stolen out of, I'm not making this
up. like really a A+ piece of car
and had a bunch of roommates and like
slept on a futon a lot.
I saved my money for manual therapy,
meaning massage therapy once a week and
like not for relaxation, for like sports
massage, fix the broken car type of
work. And that is a commitment that I
made early because I saw the dividends
and I really think it is paid off over
time and I think that is the core
component of my longevity sort of health
span
constellation of things. So that's one.
I really try to get massage work done
with a good therapist once a week. And
again a little is better than nothing.
Can't afford an hour? Do 30 minutes.
Can't afford 30 minutes? Try to find
somebody to do 15 minutes. I guarantee
you, you can find somebody who can help
you out even if they're only working on
your IT bands for 5 minutes. Like scale
back instead of going to zero. All
right. Ease of travel. I just I think
travel can be very stressful the more
people you have involved. I've got a
dog. D. So, anything that makes travel a
bit smoother, a bit easier, right? It's
like, you know, I was their first
adviser. So, again, full disclosure, but
like clear TSA precheck. anything that
makes travel a little bit easier. If
it's going to be a hassle to lug your
stuff around, if you hurt your elbow and
you've got heavy luggage, ship your
luggage, right? There's a lot you can
do. When I was spending a lot of time in
New York City, I actually stayed at the
same hotel most of the time. And what I
did at one point is I bought a trunk, a
big trunk, and I put a week's worth of
clothing and some of the supplements I
always use and a bunch of the stuff that
is in my like everyday carry in my
primary home. And I just had a trunk of
stuff that they stored in the basement
at the hotel. What did that mean? I
never had to pack. I could grab a
toothbrush and get on a plane and go to
New York and I was totally covered. had
a couple of different pairs of shoes,
had workout outfits, everything, right?
Bathing suit, didn't need anything in
one trunk. That's it. So,
ease of travel would be number two. And
then last, and I'm sure I could think of
other stuff, but healthcare for myself
and loved ones would be way up there.
And that includes in some cases, and I'm
fortunate that I have the means to do
this, but for some people like for my
parents and other people, paying for
trainers, paying for doctors, paying for
meal prep or meal delivery, right? This
kind of thing. You know, it's like
the man or woman who is well wants a
million things. You know, the sick man
or woman wants only one thing, not to be
sick, right? The injured man or woman
only wants one thing, not to be injured,
right? So just really taking care of
that is another place where I'm happy
not just to spend a lot but to
overspend. Right? So what does that
mean? That means that feeling like I
have an insurance policy or a safety net
available just in case having say you
know concierge medicine such that
god forbid something happens and I need
to get a hold of somebody at 2 a.m. on a
Wednesday, a Saturday, whatever, that I
can reach a doctor. It gives me a peace
of mind that helps with everything else,
even if I never use it. Right? It's like
having a very safe car. Even if you
never get into a head-on collision, god
forbid,
there's a reassurance that comes with
having a very, very well-rated safe car
for you and your family. So, I feel very
similar to that. Just having the ability
to do ABC, B, C, D, or E with respect to
health, fitness, medicine, specialists,
I find to be a very good investment. And
by the way, sometimes you do need that
stuff. And some of you may have seen the
announcement in the New York Times, but
I'm going to be getting very heavily
involved in a startup called Neco
Health, which is expanding to the US
very soon. It's already in the UK and
Sweden. if you want to check it out.
Co-founded by Daniel Ek, the co-founder,
longtime CEO of Spotify. Going to be
doing some very interesting stuff. So,
I'm hoping to make worldclass
preventative health care available to
millions of people.
That is just the basis of everything
else. If you don't have your health,
what do you have? All right, that's a
good one from Hannah. What's the one
most important thing you're doing to
prevent cognitive decline? Both my
parents have Alzheimer's and I'm
overwhelmed with all the hacks. I know
how you feel because I have multiple
relatives I'm caring for with
Alzheimer's right now. I would say that
if I had to pick one thing, it would be
the exercise. Okay? So, if I had to pick
one thing for cognitive health, it is
the exercise. And my conversation with
Dr. Tommy Wood gets into specifics
around this, but I'll give you one
example. doing something called the
Norwegian 4x4, which is a type of
interval training. Doing that, I want to
say three times per week for 6 months,
provided 5 years of benefits, something
like that. And zone 2 also counts for
mitochondrial health.
Alzheimer's, frankly, is very poorly
understood. And I think we're still in
the dark ages in a lot of respects. I
don't totally believe actually often
don't believe and I'm no doctor. I don't
play one on the internets. This is just
my personal experience but the remove
amalloid beta and towangles and all will
be well hypothesis which a lot of
therapeutics are predicated on. I really
don't buy it. I think a lot of it is
vascular dementia and some of it
certainly is mitochondrial dysfunction.
So I'm looking at things like I am
taking uraliththna myself for checking
in some respects a mitochondrial box
paying a lot of attention to insulin
sensitivity and glucose disposal. Again
that comes back to the weight training
but also doing plenty of intermittent
fasting and so on. There is a supplement
called that I think is pretty
interesting. It's basically a
sulforophane precursor plus a few other
ingredients that I think help with like
enzyatic conversion and things like
that. But if I had to pick one, it would
be the exercise. And then there's lots
of other stuff I do, right? Like I don't
know if you guys can see it, but like
you know there's a barrel sauna over
there. Sauna use is very interesting.
Heat shock proteins, etc. So, I'm
throwing a lot at it because it
terrifies the living hell out of me. But
I think you can pop all the pills you
want and
cobble together all sorts of mini
interventions, but if you're not doing
the exercise, if you're not eating good
food, if you're spiking your glucose
constantly over and over again and
always eating by the clock and never
doing any type of intermittent fasting,
and by intermittent fasting, I'm talking
about along the lines of a researcher
named Mark Matson. So, at least 16 hours
of fasting, preferably more, so that you
deplete glycogen in your liver, and
switch to some ketone production.
If you're only cobbling together a lots
of pills and potions, I don't think
that's going to do it, but I'm throwing
everything in the kitchen sink at it.
So, hopefully that is somewhat helpful.
If you guys think it would be
interesting, at some point I might do a
dedicated podcast, just a solo podcast
talking about exactly what I'm doing for
preserving cognitive health and
function. Again, not that I'm a doctor
or an MD, but frankly,
a lot of those folks are so siloed and
specialized that sometimes it's hard to
assemble a full picture for practical
implementation. And there are things
coming hopefully down the line. I
invested in a company called Jakcasta
Neuroscience, J O C A S T A looking at
injectable cloth for humans. Hopefully,
I think cloth K l is very interesting
and hopefully that'll be a therapeutic.
But in the meantime, guess what provokes
natural cloth production or release?
Exercise of different types. So, when in
doubt, get to the gym.
All right, guys. I think that's all I
have for right now. I'm going to hop off
and get a bite to eat since I haven't
had anything since a small breakfast.
And
I think we're going to wind down and
come to a close in just a few moments.
So, thank you everybody for the
questions. Thank you for tuning in from
around the world. And for those people
who might be listening to this if we
publish it, uh we will have show notes
linking to all sorts of stuff that I
mentioned at tim.blogmpodcast
blog/mpodcast.
And I'm not sure what the hell you would
search to find this particular episode,
but you're smart people. I'll let you
figure it out. But the show notes will
be at tim.blog/mpodcast.
And once again, everybody, thanks for
tuning in and hope to do another one of
these soon.